With artificial intelligence, it seems
really it's so good already, but
compared to what it's going to be, I
still see it as really stupid because
it's it jumps to the wrong conclusions a
lot of times when I'm using it. It
doesn't ask me questions. It gives you
responses that are way too verbose. And
it's like, "No, that's not even what I
asked and you just [music] wasted a
million tokens."
>> Terrestrial compute AI data, all very
exciting. Heck, we might even talk about
a little bit of space base because I've
got one burning question that not too
many people can answer. That's why I'm
joined by Jordan Geisler from The
Limiting Factor. You may know him
[music] as the battery guru, the guy who
reads all the white papers, the guy who
understands the business so well that
the battery engineers at Tesla I've
spoken to said that he must have an
inside man and he doesn't. He just knows
how to read and [music] understand what
he's reading. I got Jordan Geisler with
me. I'm Brian. Welcome to Future Ozo.
>> [music]
[singing]
>> So, Jordan, I don't know if you know
this, but you have a channel on YouTube.
Is that correct? Am I reading that
right?
>> That is right.
>> [laughter]
>> Look at those
thumbnails. Join him. They are. They
look really great. And if that's just
not classy enough, you can also join him
over on X.
>> Much less classy.
>> [laughter]
>> I mean, the real problem is both of
those places let anybody in.
So, you did a fantastic video on
terrestrial compute. You went back and
looked at a video you'd made a year ago
and said, "This is what I envision these
three big dogs." We've already got one
big dog. We're going to add two more big
dogs. And in terms of where it would be
located, where it would be situated, you
were going on the best information
available, but the best information
available did not have a
additional land yet, land that was added
later. So, what we ended up seeing was
Whoops.
Seeing was this instead.
Uh
>> Uh, they got some land across the
street, but harder over there,
and what's all this where we may have
believed the building could have gone?
>> Uh, it looks like uh cooling and energy
and battery related stuff, but there is
that further to the left, it looks like
they are going to be putting another
building there, which is going to be the
third building. I don't know if that's
going to be enough to hit that full
million that Elon originally said for
Colossus 2, but it's three buildings
just in a different layout than what I
suggested.
>> That is uh and you can correct my math
here, but I what I'm seeing is a lot of
batteries.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> That's a lot of juice.
>> This year alone
SpaceX AI has spent $329
million on Megapacks.
And we do see heat exchangers and yes,
other power-related things. On this
third building, it could just be taller.
I haven't seen it from the ground.
Elon's companies will use vertical space
when necessary,
and maybe that's better. Uh
tough to say. If you're running out of
land, which no matter how much of it his
companies acquire, he seems to always be
running out of land. Uh so, my one
question about space I wanted to ask
because there's quite a bit of real
estate up there at the moment.
Uh a big
satellite that does big compute that
pulls a lot of juice,
that's not going to need very much
battery, is it?
>> No. If you're in space and you have
access to constant sun, if you're in
that uh what is it? The type of orbit.
It's escaping me right now, but it's
sun-synchronous orbit, I think is the
word for it, where you're constantly
facing the sun. Uh the you won't need
the batteries to cover periods where
there's no sun. You need the batteries
to provide extra juice when there's
extra juice is needed for the compute.
So, it's um
not not what a lot of people think.
>> Right. So, uh the battery is just to
cover the night time and if you're in
the correct orbit, there is no night
time.
>> Yeah. So, it's a different theory than
why you need batteries on Earth. Well,
here on Earth you need the battery.
Yeah, there's a couple different reasons
you need a batteries for data centers uh
here on Earth. One of them is to cover
night time and another one is to cover
uh peak power usage. Whereas in space,
you're just going to need it for one of
those things whereas uh the peak power
those bursts where you need a little bit
of extra power.
>> Now, uh anybody can build a data center,
Jordan. You and I can build a data
center.
I think I can predict with 100% accuracy
how well that would go. Not well is what
I is what my build would be, but even
people who think they know what they're
doing often make mistakes.
And very few companies have the ability
to pull off things that the chip
manufacturer themselves didn't see
coming, the chip designers really.
Nvidia did not believe you could get a
coherent cluster of 100,000 plus
uh and lo and behold they did. Do they
have some competencies in deploying uh
data centers?
>> It sure looks like it based on the
evidence. They're able to uh SpaceX/xAI
formerly, they've proven to be able to
deploy these data centers much faster
than anybody else and that's not just
the data at center itself, but all the
supporting infrastructure for that. Uh
they're stepping on some toes in the
process.
>> [laughter]
>> But, um they seem to be uh uh just do it
and then ask for forgiveness afterwards.
[laughter]
So,
>> Yeah, I mean there's philosophical
approaches that you can analyze, but I'm
not here to do that. I'm just looking at
the actual numbers and whatnot. Uh so,
it seems that
xAI overbuilt
by a lot
as evidenced by the fact that xAI runs
just fine
>> [snorts]
>> and can lease out billions of dollars of
compute.
How did that happen? Why did that
happen?
>> It's extremely profitable. So, what
they're doing is they're building the
excess uh compute. They're They're
building as much compute as they
possibly can. They're using the compute
they need for their uh internal needs,
and then everything else they're selling
to other people. And it's
extraordinarily
Basically, you can pay these data
centers off. Whatever you build, you can
pay it off within about a year.
>> If I had told you before the earnings
came out that they could pay it off in 2
years, you might have thought I was a
little crazy, right?
>> If you're not following the space, then
yeah, it's uh Well, if you would have
told me earlier this year that they
would be able to pay it off in a year,
I'd be like, "Oh, mhm maybe." So, yeah,
to your point, it's shocking.
>> It's a shocking number.
And if you look at just This is again,
I'm showing slides from Jordan's video.
You can go check it out, too. It's free.
Uh but I got to check it out early
because I'm a supporter on Patreon. If
you love Jordan's work, you can support
him on Patreon. He only makes a few
videos a month because they're amazing.
And trying to make them even even two a
week would be prohibitive. You'd need a
whole team. Well, what are we looking at
here? This is some big numbers.
>> Yeah, so it's just the These are the
different companies that XAI/SpaceX
has rented their compute out, too.
>> But those are big companies. Surely,
they could build it themselves even
better.
>> Yeah, they they just aren't getting
enough, and uh
SpaceX is able to build surplus to their
needs, whereas everybody else Nobody
else is able to do that.
>> Ain't it crazy that that Google would
come to you and ask to rent? Oh.
>> Yeah. There's There's so many There's so
many different levels to this game. So,
it's You need a whole ecosystem of
players to make the industry uh a really
strong success in the United States. So,
yeah, they they might compete on
individual products, but if you have
something that you can sell to somebody
else and they need it, it's in the best
interest of both parties. So, it's not
as cutthroat as everybody thinks it is.
They are competing fiercely, but they're
also um
taking advantage of the fact that
there's other people in the ecosystem.
>> Yes. And what I tell people is
it's not enough that I can build a data
center cheaper in a year.
I need that compute today. I need need
it. If I don't have it, I may not
survive. Not every company is going to
survive. You can't fall behind.
>> If you're paying Yeah, to your point, if
you're paying extra for it, it doesn't
matter because you're
it's critical to your survival and it's
critical to your revenue. For instance,
if something costs a dollar and you make
$2 off of it, are you still going to pay
a $1.50 for it? Probably.
>> [laughter]
>> Well,
and that is a very good comparison
because I can
in a year's time, I can start selling it
for a dollar. But I may be gone by then.
And if I'm not actually It's like doing
drop shipping. And so, if it's a $1.50
and I don't have to do the work,
I'm still making the 50 cents.
I mean, that makes sense at that point.
>> [snorts]
>> Now, of course, uh because it is SpaceX,
they're not going to grow anymore.
They're they're done with that story.
Wait, Hank Taipale I just noticed this,
uh Memphis, what's going on there?
>> Okay, there's a lot of And this
I'm glad you asked this question because
I made this video
I put it out 3 weeks ago and it's
already significantly changed since
then. So, they have currently existing
about 1.5 to 2 gigawatts of compute in
Memphis, total.
And
at the time that I made this video, uh
semi-analysis was estimated they had at
least two gigawatts of power energy
generation lined up beyond that. So, I
just took that as a given, as a
baseline. And, uh, yeah, that would mean
doubling the compute next year if they
installed another two gigawatts. But,
what they said at the earnings call, of
course, is that that could be 5 to 10
gigawatts in total versus, um, four.
So, significantly more ambitious than
I'm when I put
than what I put in this video.
>> Yes. And, to give some scale to this, to
the power consumption, because
it's easy to, uh, just see big numbers
and you know, I don't I don't know what
it means.
To give you an idea, uh, what we're
looking at is
a medium-size city of a half million
people needs a peak capacity
of 500 megawatts to 1.5 gigawatts.
Uh, so, we're talking about little bit
of power is one way to put it. Another
way to put it is Memphis's entire power
draw. Boy, that's too small to see.
Memphis's entire power draw.
Their record maximum hourly demand
was 3 and 1/2 gigs. So, this data center
will pull more power than the city it is
next to, which is And if we're talking 6
to 10, that's New York City.
>> Yeah. That's, uh, 6 to 10 full-size
nuclear reactors.
>> [laughter]
>> Yes.
And they're going to be doing it with
gas generation,
uh, which is just, you know, dozens or
hundreds of, uh,
gas generators, depending on what type
you're type you're talking about.
>> Now, my question on those gas
generators, with that many, will I hear
them from Washington State?
>> Maybe.
>> [laughter]
>> Not I mean, not that loud, but it will
be substantial.
>> Yeah, they're going to be throwing out a
lot of heat, a lot of emissions, a lot
of Yeah. So, that's that's some
relationship management going on there.
But, there it's natural gas, so it's
better than what we had, you know, 20,
30 years ago using coal generation and
other other types of generation, so.
>> Yeah. Uh
now, there's
big risk, big reward,
big cost to deploy. Now, of course,
XAI's going to be getting the best
rates. And
what Nvidia wants is these chips to get
out there and get used.
Uh
they're getting the latest greatest.
They're getting them in, it appears,
reasonable quantity.
>> [snorts]
>> And as these other players say, "You
know what? We're just going to rent
instead of buy." Maybe they're dropping
off the list. I would rather have
I would rather have a handful of really
big customers than 10 million small
customers. It's just a lot easier to
manage.
Uh you can solve
one problem one time instead of the same
problem 10,000 times in terms of
the money in it. Because it looks like
as fast as they can build it, they can
deploy it, and they can
uh two customers, two paying customers.
Let's talk about Let's talk about this
number.
Uh 72 billion a year potentially
with 440,000
GPUs. Uh how many
locations is that?
>> It depends if you're talking about
buildings or locations, cuz right now
there's just two locations, Colossus 1
and Colossus 2. Colossus 1 is just one
building, and Colossus 2 is two
buildings, and um soon to be three.
>> Mhm. Well, I [snorts] think uh
adjacent is close enough. Uh
yeah. So, do we know of other locations
they're considering?
>> My understanding is no, and I was
reading some analysis this morning
saying,
"All right, if they want to build this
additional compute next year, what
they've said, we need they need to
announce at least one more major site
because it's getting pretty tight now at
Colossus 2.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah.
Uh weirdly, you know, again, you buy
the land you can and then you do your
best from there. Now, you you did some
revenue calculations where you
determined that the cost to build this
out would be what, a hundred and some
billion?
>> 120 billion for 2 GW of compute based on
uh Gavin Baker's estimates, which he's
he seems to be
tracking this very closely and in
contact with a lot of the
uh people who are in the know. So, but
what I did in order to
to try to match the bullishness of
everybody else in this space, cuz people
are very bullish, is rather than saying
it costs $60 billion per GW, I'm
assuming it's going to cost uh
$50 billion per GW, assuming that Elon
gets mate's rates and he's able to
deploy it much more efficiently than
anybody else, just giving it uh
the most aggressive assumptions here.
And in terms of their revenue, I'm
assuming $50 billion per GW per year.
That is whatever you build, you can pay
it off within a year.
>> Mhm.
>> Now, a lot of people uh assume, okay,
well, that means it's fully
self-funding.
Not really.
Because
there's going to be a lag from when you
give the organization the money and you
build these data centers and you get
them online, start generating the
revenue, and then that actually starts
showing up on your earnings report. So,
if you're just building 2 GW per quarter
for the next year, say 8 GW,
um and you're say you have a 3 to
6-month lag, that's a hundred to two
hundred billion-dollar lag.
>> Mhm.
>> So, it's uh there's going to be a lot of
self-funding going on, that's for sure.
But, you're still going to need
a lot of capital above and beyond that,
which is probably going to come from
like Nvidia or
>> Yeah, I'm sure they can find the
capital.
>> Well, they do have a strong cash reserve
at this point, which they will draw down
while that income is ramping.
And worst-case scenario, you slow the
pace a little bit, which I think they
would only do if they could see that
they don't have the customers lined up
ready to go.
I I'm not worried about that part of it
because
they don't have enough money, but I can
see where the money's coming from. I
don't have enough money to build 2
million cars this year, but if I sell a
bunch in Q1,
I mean, there we go.
So, I think that's
a reasonable way to do it. So, on that
front, now I know in your video you made
this wild claim that I do not believe
that you cannot predict the future. So,
I'm going to challenge you on that
and say, what are the risks to the
upside and the downside? Let's start
with the with the upside risks. The
upside variables, maybe the compute
rentals cost more in the next 6 months
to 12 months.
Maybe they maybe they pay them down pay
them off in 11 or 10 months instead of
12. That's possible.
>> It's certainly well
to that point, a lot of people are
saying that they they might be able to
run out these new
Vera Rubin GPUs for a lot more.
Which is is certainly potentially the
case.
But, there could also be unexpected
expenses. So, I tried to develop a
reasonable All right, so let's go a
little bit low on the cost of actually
deploying it and go a little bit high on
how much revenue they can earn for it.
But, I I go double like a lot of like
some people are saying.
So, it's like I tried to not go too
aggressive in any direction, just kind
of hit a middle ground there. So, they
certainly could. And another
And it's not just the terrestrial
compute uh that they're going to be
earning money off of. They're also going
to be scaling cursor and uh Starlink and
several other products. So, there are
potential for surprises there in terms
of uh generating revenue.
But, with all that said, even SpaceX
themselves and the writers who were
involved are saying, "Well, we expect
them to be cash flow negative until 2030
to 2035." So, I was saying at least for
the next year or two.
And um
I think that's a fair assumption. Put it
that way, given that several other
people in the know are assuming that
could continue for half a decade to a
decade.
>> The other side of it is, what if uh it
the demand collapses? And I don't mean
demand in total. I don't mean people
will stop using AI.
I mean that uh
it is very likely that the number of
players we see today will contract in
the future.
And that as processors get faster and
faster,
the need to expand at insane paces maybe
reduced. What if the rents go down? What
if the power costs go What if it just
doesn't make sense to rent it out
anymore?
Is the risk there that they've got a
whole bunch of compute that they got at
a tremendous discount due to leasing it
out? Now, they just have
infinite in-house compute.
>> Um in terms of demand, I think there's
pretty much going to be infinite demand
because it's uh there's so much that
can still be done with AI. I'm trying to
think of an example here, but um
the more AI you use, the more AI you
use. The agents have their own agents
now, and there's only a small proportion
of the population actually using this
compute. And for each new model that
they create, they're actually
um
you know, expanding the amount of memory
re- memory that's required. And that's
more of a a memory thing though.
>> More parameters.
>> Yeah, more parameters. Larger models,
etc. They they can just do more. But
then there's after you get So right now,
you have programmers are getting a lot
of utility out of AI. And as it becomes
more functional, more and more people
are going to get utility out of it. Um
and that's just with text-based type
artificial intelligence. But what about
when you start moving to real-world
intelligence, where you're not just
processing letters and numbers, you're
also processing visual data and audio
data. Uh and that's going to require
orders of magnitude more compute there.
So there's just in several directions,
we're going to need several orders of of
magnitude more compute. And to tease
that out, that would take a a longer
discussion, but that's in short I I I
agree with the consensus.
>> Well, I'm Yes, go ahead.
>> No, um
but with all that said, there's always a
risk that you have some surplus compute
on hand. I don't think that's going to
happen
given all the forecasts, but it's it's
always a risk and it's unavoidable.
>> Well, when you're not using surplus
compute, it doesn't cost as much money
to own. It's when it's running that it
really gets you. And these chips do not
degrade by age so much as by cycle. Uh
much like solar panels or wind turbines,
if you stop using them for the day, uh
they do not age as much.
Um [snorts] I do have uh some big
thoughts coming up. I will share them,
but first I wanted to mention uh that uh
you can subscribe not to one, but to
both of us. Yes, uh do you remember
where this was taken?
>> Uh at the uh Giga
uh Cyber Rodeo.
>> Yeah, that's right. The the day after
party uh at the uh
place by the airport there. That was a
lot of fun. And that's genuinely what we
look like. This is filtered right here.
So, my thought is there is infinite
demand for AI and what it does at a
price.
And I'm not convinced that the price it
really costs today is some is an amount
that consumers would pay because a lot
of companies are selling their tokens
for less than they cost or giving them
away. Chat GPT has probably as many
users as there are people who have ever
lived because in a lot of places,
including the US, when people run out of
tokens, they create a second account.
So,
it's uh
I don't know
how much the price needs to fall
for businesses
to use it more. [clears throat] I mean,
how much more output We've seen
companies that accidentally spend
hundreds of thousands, millions of
dollars on tokens unaware that they were
racking up these bills.
Um I did see a guy who said he
accidentally burnt through his entire
month of tokens because he said, "Hey,
can you give me a summary of this PDF?"
And he had it on like the most intense
mode and he spent like $300 getting up
really amazing summary of a PDF.
He's like, "Why is it running for so
long? Golly." I think the better
compute, the better algorithms
will increase the efficacy per dollar
spent, but I don't know how quickly
because unlike you, I can't predict the
future. Now, I know you said you can,
but I don't know, man. You've been
pretty good in the past. How big of a
risk is that?
That that companies will say, "Look,
this AI bill is just too darn much."
>> The way I look at that is that there's
leading edge companies right now that
they're getting the most benefit out of
that. And they get
a certain amount of boost to their
productivity given the amount of
um
give given how far advanced the
technology is. Well, it's I think it's
probably 90 to 95% of the businesses out
there still haven't worked out how to
to get that juice out of the lemon.
So, I think it's you know,
there's still a lot more companies that
need to be able to to
take advantage of what's already there.
So,
just in terms of that total addressable
market, that's going to expand just in
terms of the number of people who are
using it productively. And then on top
of that,
it's in terms of these current
foundational models, I view it as
uh
decreasing return on investment as they
they get better cuz they're already
pretty good and they're really they're
really good at coding already. And I
don't know how much better they're
they're going to to get. So, there will
be some improvement there in terms of
how much value people get out of these
models, but I think most of it is just
expanding it to new people.
Filling in the total addressable market,
yeah.
>> There are people who don't use AI yet. I
didn't use AI for the longest time
because it wasn't reliable. It wasn't
good. Uh but bear in mind, ideally, it's
today and tomorrow, it'll be the worst
it's ever been. Now, that's runs
contrary to Google's philosophy. Their
products tend to get worse every day. Uh
so, that's great and I still have all my
Google Home smart speakers, but they're
getting dumb.
Uh
>> Well, at the at the beginning, Google
like I remember like the excitement
every time they didn't did a new
software release and things were getting
better and better and better. And then
it's just like peaked and now it's like
all the talent went into AI or someplace
else. But I I I do feel like AI is
getting better uh continuously and who
knows how long that's going to go for.
>> Well, I would say the focus was on
making the best product, and then the
shift became to make the most profitable
product. And the most profitable search
results are not what you asked for, but
a bunch of sponsored stuff and something
close enough that you'll do another
search.
And as a result, instead of using Google
as my go-to for research, I use Grok and
say, "Just give me all the citations I
need so I can go and read it myself."
And it works. If I've got a part of a
song stuck in my head, I can find it,
uh, with all of the words being
incorrect. It's pretty amazing.
>> For the average use, like like you
remember PCs when you first got PCs in
the 1980s, you had actually know some
heavy-hitting stuff, some technical
information, in order to build a PC and
get it running.
>> [laughter]
>> I remember lots of, uh,
uh, excitement when my dad would get a
new PC when I was a kid, and it would
take him a while to get up and running,
and there was lots of issues. Now,
they're they're pretty much plug and
play. And so, when you make it easier
for people to access, I don't know
whatever you call the harness or
whatever it is, just how it interacts
with people, you're going to expand the
total addressable market. And with
artificial intelligence,
it seems really it's so good already,
but compared to what it's going to be, I
still see it as really stupid.
Uh, because it's
it jumps to the wrong conclusions a lot
of times when I'm using it. It doesn't
ask me questions. It gives you responses
that are way too verbose. And it's like,
"No, that's not even what I asked, and
you just wasted a million tokens
>> [laughter]
>> giving me information that I didn't
need, when all I wanted was just a a
sentence." What you should have done, if
you were truly intelligent as an AI, you
would have listened to my question, and
like when we're having a discussion,
rather than just spitting out an answer,
often we're listening to each other.
We're feeling out the context of each
other's minds, having a little bit of a
mind meld, and the the conversation
evolves a lot more efficiently. And
that's what I see is lacking with AI. It
doesn't ask probing questions
given the
given all that it knows in the context
to
be truly helpful.
And that's what we need for humanoid
robots. It needs to not only understand
human conversation like that, to
understand what they need truly. Um they
also need to understand the world like
that. And that's that's another
conversation, but I think that's why a
truly useful humanoid robot is probably
3 to 4 years away.
>> Mhm. Well, uh we could debate on truly
useful because Unitree's about to go
public, but
>> Well, in the in the context of being
useful for your average person. I think
like in the next year or two or three
years, there's going to be huge market
there for like factories and people who
know how to talk to the robot to get it
to do what they want to do. Just like a
year or two ago programmers were doing
that. And now it's you can be
conversational with the programming
language.
>> I don't know if you've seen it, guys.
Maybe I'll pop a link in the description
or up in the corner, but I used Grok as
my local tour guide and FSD as my
driver.
And I had it drive me all over my town,
and I just asked questions. I I looked
at things and said, "What's that?" And
it told me. And because I did it in my
town, I was able to know what was true
and not. And I would say that while not
100% accurate, uh it was more accurate
than any local tour guide I've ever had.
Uh because they love to vamp, just fill
in some stuff here and there.
And it is important to be conversational
because there are times when I'll ask
Grok something and then interrupt and
say, "No, no, no, no. I meant this."
Or, you know, I realize
Yeah.
>> It's a constant source of entertainment
for people in the car with me cuz I ask
Grok a question and it the first
sentence it always gets it right, and
then it just continues for five other
sentences. So, I ask it a question then
I say shut up and then it asks
>> [laughter]
>> another question I say shut up. So, like
oh, you bicker with this thing like
you're in a relationship with it.
>> Yeah. Well, and listening is important.
I remember one time my boss said to me,
"Brian, are you even listening?" And I
thought, "What a weird way to start a
conversation."
So, I didn't stay there very long, but
uh guys in the comments, what have we
missed? What do we misunderstand? Leave
it, I beg of you. If you get a chance,
check out The Limiting Factor. He's
still popping out gems uh all the time.
Great stuff, as you know. And uh because
I am, as of this video, surely by now,
in Nepal, uh there will be a second
video coming where we're going to be
talking about 4680. Is it obsolete? Did
we miss the boat? Of course not, but uh
I'll uh explain it more there.